‏I [موسيقى] to ask you because I know
that you one people.
[موسيقى]
طيب
كل جزئيه كنا نمر عنها كل
[موسيقى]
>> يعني يمكن ان يكون السؤال اسهل علي ان
سالتيني وقلت لي ما هو الشيء الذي لم
يختلف
عن ما
[موسيقى]
[موسيقى] تفضل
‏from the New York Times. I'm Rachel
Abrams and this is the daily.
Earli this month after Israel and Hamas
reached fire agreement, the Israeli
military said it would pull back from
certain areas of Gaza.
‏This meant that some Palestinians who
been displaced to the south could try to
return home to the north.
الو مرحبا عم تسمعني
>> الو
>> [موسيقى]
>> لا استطيع ان اصف هذه المشاعر
لان
من اللحظه الاولى التي سمعت بانها
الامر لثانيتين بل انني اخذت القرار على
الفور بانني ساعود
اكتبونا
الله
stron
‏Is bom
more
are displaced fames from across gaza
refuge wai to the
week
was
صوت الناس بتزقف وبتهدتف
يعني
ساهر الغرا
[موسيقى]
هل في كان مشهد اثر فيك؟
>> النسبه الاكبر كانوا اطفال يعني ما كان
يتعدى عمرهم الع سنين
في وجوههم بيضحكوا
انتجت على الافراح ويعني بعبروا عن مشاكل
وكان يحكوا كلام واحد
خلصنا نموت بعد
>> كنت بجهز قصه قصه مصوره انه بدي اقدم لها
لمس
فكانت
الواحد بتات
فهذا شي يعني في الواحد
بعد ما روحت من خان يونس وخلصت التصوير
زي حاجز
الباب بينفتح ويهجم مره واحده
فكان دخول
المشهد كان يعني بتحكي انه الاف الفلسطين
>> [موسيقى]
[موسيقى]
>> حواليهم ناس بيمشوا في بياع ببيع
على الطريق اه على الشارع مب
‏some peopleadصلع
[موسيقى]
وقت يعني
انت حسيت انه الناس اختلفت
اكيد طبعا
يعني الناس من خلال
يعني هو الموقف اللي بكونوا عايشين فيه
لعب دور فرق لما يكون الشخص نازحور
>> [موسيقى]
[ضحك]
>> الو
>> الو مرحبا نضال
>> مراحب مراحب يا هلا نضال كحيل
>> والله من حسن حظك ان انا موجود في كافي
واه اوكي عندي انترنت حاليا ‏Unlike and
thousands of other palestans who walking
that day, was a cafe was
ولكن الحقيقه انه بيتي انا تحديدا
اللحظه
المعلومات
>> [موسيقى]
>> 31
>> الا انا بتذكر طبعا هو بيتو
والدي
يعني هو كان عباره
المدخل
هو قديم ‏And it was oldernal
complications of buildings
there was
>> عارفه ريحه الدفا لما بيكون في بره مطر
وبرد وعارفه لما بكون في [ضحك] اه هيك
>> ولما بكون بره هيك في حر يعني بتفوت البيت
تعملي هيك فاهمه علي يعني شعور الراحه
هذاغزاوي
يعني بالفلسطيني بالغزاوي
الريحه مليانه الفه ومحبه
>> [موسيقى]
>> غرفتي
يعني انا غرفتي مثلا كانت ملازل
>> [موسيقى]
>> يعني البيت
المكان
>> [موسيقى]
>> ما فيش عندي كلمات غير انه انا يعني اشعر
مازلت مصمم ان هو وطن صغير جو الوطني
>> [موسيقى]
>> عندك بعد امل انه بيتك يكون موجود؟
>> انا بتمنى يعني اتمنى حتى لو كان
‏So I hope that the house is standing.
‏I mean I really have no words even if
it's just the roof I'll bring a tarp and
I'll just house out of it.
نقدر نعيش فيه راح ا روح اعيش فيه ارجع
>> [موسيقى]
[موسيقى]
>> ‏A few miles away from
traveling
he took photos as he went of head home
on a road crowded by of rocks and fring
of buildings
but was not only taking photos of other
people's journey
العافيه
تل الهواء
وصلتله [موسيقى]
ما دخلت جو بس
انا
وفي كمان بيت
كل بيوت
احنا بنفيش
ولا بيت
بطلع في الشوارع يعني في شغلات كثير انا
قعدت
على انه انا بعرف
الجاتو
فانا بتذكر انه هل هو هذا المحل او لا
كان بدل العرايس
فصراحه الواحد بحس حاله انه بدون هويه
هذا المكان انا
وبتصير
اعيش
مش بدنا وقت لما نراجعه زي ما كان
>> يعني طبيعه كلامهم كانت انه عشان ايش صار
كل هذا وايش استفدنا من الحرب اللي
استفدنا من الحرب وانه الحرب هذه
وضيعت حياتنا وضيعتنا
هذا الكلام
مش
الكلام
>> رحت لمنطقه
شمال غرب مدينه غزه اللي هي منطقه شارع
الجلاء
هي منطقه منطقه حيويه كثير وكنا ندخل
خصوصا
ومحلات ثانيه مول تجاري او
فكنت يعني اول ما وصلت
رفعت
بس قعدت اتذكر
طلعت في المشهد هيك لقيت على اليمين وعلى
اليسار قوم
>> بس كوم حجار على اليمين وكوم حجار على
اليسار وفي النص [موسيقى] مليان مليان
لدرجه من كثر الدمار فاحنا صرنا نشوف حتى
نشوف البحر
>> [موسيقى]
>> لانه كان في قبل في عمارات مغطيه اليوم
هذه العمارات وقعت
[موسيقى]
لو كان في شويه امل فهذا الامل
لو بدنا نقعد ايش بدنا نقعد وين بدنا نقعد
>> زي اللي اجاني شعور انه انتهى كل شي
[موسيقى]
>> والمناطق السكنيه الكثير الكثيره هذ ماضلش
يعني كلها كوم حجار
‏And it just like this entire place
[موسيقى] people used to like enity is
just gone.
It's just a pile of rocks.
[موسيقى]
We be right back.
‏In a neor in the northwest of Gaza City
just across from where the photal was
there a city
this is whereold boy named wased earli
this year
when the seaside road reopened his
father
paid to get
‏made back trailer with 20 other people
allaving
the was only stop in a larger journey
wasn't going home to rebild his old life
he knew that he never could
he was going home to say goodbye
when arrived in the cemetery [موسيقى]
he dug up his son's body he put him in a
white bag and carried him on roughly
>> [موسيقى]
>> الو
>> السلام عليكم
>> كيفك حسين
الله يرضى عليك
[موسيقى]
المركز الاول حسام عوده من فلسطين
>> الله اكبر
>> كانت حياتي قبل الحرب يعني لاعب كمال
اجسام
‏I was
[موسيقى]
paraly
>> وفي السنه اللي فتحنا فيها الجيم اشتغلت
معايا في جيم لكن في فتره
كانت
خالد
محمد
يوسف محمد الايام
قريب مننا
باقي الايام كنت اخذ مثلا زيارات عائليه
معي
البحر البحر قريب منا
شغلات زي هذه
حياتي طبيعيه مثلي مثل اي شخص
قلبت حياتنا راسا على اخب
استشهدت عائلتي انا في بدايه الحرب في
تاريخ 29/1023
الساعه 8 ونص صباح
انت كنت وجود لما صار هذا القصف اللي عم
تحكي لي عنه
>> هو تم قصف الطابق الارضي بصاروخ يعني
الطابق هذا
من
>> كانت كل كل اللي بشوفه هو سواد قدام عيني
فانا في لحظتها يعني سمعت
ف سمعت زوجتي بتنادي علي
سالتها ويند
ولكن ما ضرق
ولكن ما ضرروا من
فانا متاكد ان بنتي كانت معاهم يعني لانه
هي تشتري
شويه مصا
فاخذتهم ونزلت فيهم يعني
فجات في في المكان الطابق اللي فجاءت يعني
ما اي
وكل الموجودين في المكان كانوا عباره عن
اشلاء يعني ما فيش
راحت ستها الصبح فصار الحدث وهي موجوده
عندهم
10 people
احنا نزحنا ما يقارب سب
وعشنا في مدرسه ونزحنا مخيمشنا في
المستشفى مرات اهing
up
the rubble as best they ‏inside and
tried to make two rooms and a makeshift
bathroom.
Husin never let his sons out of his
sight. His muscle body was getting
thinner and thinner, but he still made
his sons feel safe, feel protected.
The family stayed there for around 4
months until one night in May, the
fighting got so intense they felt like
they had to leave.
اتفقت انا والسواق الساعه 12 الظهر بده
يجي يجي
طلعت من البيت اروح اجيب السواق وارجع
مجرد ما رجعت
في انفجار حصل في نفس المكان اللي انا
عايش في
>> شفت يعني البيت اللي انقصف هو بيتي كنت
بعيد عنه
>> المكان كان كله غبره سودا وسكن ما يعني
صعب صعب جدا انك تشوف اي شيء في المكان ف
توجهت للمكان بسرعه
فجت هذا المكان المصوف هو بيتنا ولكن
الاس بعد البيت كله
فسمعت صوت واحد
فبعد ساعه ونص من المحاولات يعني الانتشار
من
فكانت هذه زوجتين ولكن كلورس
ونجيت باعجوبه يعني
اما اولاد الثلاثه اللي هو خالد ويوسف
ومحمد استشهدوا ف في نفس اللحظه
ابن محمد الصغير بعمر اربع سنوات زوجتي
بالضبط
محمد
اشوف
ولا اعرف انه كانوا عايشين
عباره عن
>> والله هو شعور هو شعور العجز يعني انه انا
اول شيء انا انظلمت
مرتين تمث
راح اجيب سواي
يعني ايش ايش ارتكب اطفالي لحد
البيت
انا في نفس اليوم اللي استشهد في الصبح
الساعه ت الصبح ف كانوا مبسوطين كثير كثير
ايش نفسك قاللي انا نفسي تجيبلي بلاي
ستيشن
ويوسف طلب مني اللي هو فزبا فما
محمد الصغيرت
هذ اخر طلبات لهمخر امنيه ‏That was that
was their last wish. That was the last
things that they wished for.
I asked Hin if there might be any reason
his building was bombed, whether it
might have been aet for the Israel
military. He said no.
‏He told me that he's not political nor
is he a member of Hamas and neither were
any of his family members who were
killed in either of the strikes. We have
not found any evidence that goes against
that.
We do know that one of Hussein's cousins
was a senior leader in Hamas who was
targeted and killed in a searate Israel
air strike. But Hussein told me he
wasn't close to that cousin. ‏He has
dozens of cousins and hed only seen this
particular one a couple times in his
life.
Ultimately Hussein rejects the idea that
his building was hit because of his
cousin's affiliation with Hamas. He says
his family was killed indiscriminately.
‏Most of those killed in both strikes on
his building were women and children.
We asked the Israeli military about the
two strikes. We provided them with the
coordinates of Hussein's building and
the names and ID numbers of those
killed. They provided no reason or
explanation for the strikes and didn't
dispute Hin's account of the story.
[موسيقى]
‏The days that followed the second air
strike were frantic for Hussein. His
wife Ra had been seriously injured.
Hussein rushed her back and forth
between several hospitals. After
multiple visits, they found out she
suffered a broken and dislocated pelvis.
She also had severe nerve damage. The
injuries left her partially paralyzed
from the hips down.
‏Doctors told her she'd require a
lengthy surgery, but they couldn't do
it. [موسيقى] First, because they didn't
have the medical equipment required to
do it in Gaza. And second, because the
surgery would take hours, hours in which
they could save many people's lives.
They just couldn't spend so much time on
a single patient.
The doctors told them she would have to
leave Gaza to get the operation.
‏trying to get his wife medical care was
also trying to find and b in the rubble
he looked and looked until it was no
longer safe to do so he and his wife had
to flee south
had to leave his son's b behind
he grieved his sons and he grieved over
not being able to bury them
weeks later hus asked a family friend
who was still
‏to look under the one more time to see
if could find anything. He did. He
found's body but it was too dangerous to
bearf in the family grave. So his friend
took's body south to Gaza city and
temporarily buried him in the cemetery
there.
But he never found its body.
حسين
>> وانا في مدينه غزه اخذت ابني يوسف
>> وتوجهت فيه الى مخيم جبال
>> لكن كل بقدر نعمله هو انه ادفن حبيب يوسف
رحمه الله عليه وان شاء الله الملتقى بكون
الجنه
>> وكان
صعب جدا بصراحه يعني لسه لو انا مسافر على
اقره
لميتنا في مخيم جباليا ونحاول باي طريقه
انتشال
>> بعدين توجهت لبيتي
>> رحمه الله
حاولنا انتشار خالد
اخذنا الرفات هذه
وعملنا له اللي هو جنازه بسيطه
دفنته في القبر اللي دفنت فيه يوسف ومحمد
مقبره كمان يوسف القبر اللي دفنت
هو بصراحه كان يعني ارتياح كبير ان انا
دفنت
يعني انه انا ابني موجود تحت المنزل
بعدين
انه انا ممكن ادفنهم واكر رمهم بالدفن
يعني
حتى في قبورهم يعني يكونوا موجودين مش تحت
ركام كمان
خالد يوسف المحمد
‏grave daysas came into
they were 10 and years old they wereed
next to their sister
she was
and and what about your house do you
have plans to rebuild the house do you
have any hopes for making this a home
again for you or is it just too painful
to think about لا
>> لا لا
>> نعم
>> لانه بصراحه المكان اللي انا عايش فيه
[موسيقى]
I mean at this
اخذ النصيب الاكبر في هذه الحرب من الدمار
ومن القتل
>> ولكن انا زوجتي بحتاج لعلاج يعني انا
بناشد كل شخص يعني ‏My wife, I'm thinking
about her the most. I want her to
restart her life. You know, she still
[موسيقى] needs to do the surgery that
she needs in order to heal. ‏And we are
just trying to figure out how to make it
by with the rest of my wife's life.
لما صارت الهدنه يعني شعور هو سيء جدا
وحلو في نفس الوقت انه توقفت الارض توقف
شن
عشان يروحوا على البحر وعشان يرجعوا على
المدرسه وعشان يشتعدهم
اخذهم على البحر حيه
كان يحبوها نفسهم يروحوا يطيروا طائره
ورقيه
هذه كانت اكثر شغله
ما تمكنت اني احميهم
حدا كثير بصراحه يعني كل السنتين الاخيرات
عشناهم مع بعض يعني انا كنت انام انا
واياهم
انه
بعاد عني فللاسف وقت الحادث يعني فصلتنا
كان معي انا
>> فهذا اكثر حدث يعني بقلمني بصراحه
>> عن جد انا كثير حزين يعني انه انتهت الحرب
مافوش
يعني فتحوا عليهم على الدنيا
>> [موسيقى]
[موسيقى]
>> ه على الله
>> بابا
>> اليوم انا وخالد ويوسف وحموده
>> حبينا نمسي عليكم يلا قول لهم يلا باي
>> باي
>> ارجع لمدرستي ارجع لعنطيتي ارجع لص
>> ايش اخبارك
>> منيح
>> اه
>> وانت يا يوسف
>> كيف حالك
>> منيح
>> وانت خالد كيف
>> حالك يعني احنا في السابق صف البيت هذا
اللي احنا موجودين فيه واحنا موجودين
ربما
>> [موسيقى]
>> ‏un எம ‏Since the beginning of the war,
90% of G have been displaced many of
them repeatedly. [موسيقى]
Hundreds of thousands of them have
traveled from the south to the north,
back to their homes since the seas
began.
But many on this journey have found only
rubble.
‏The UN also estimates that nearly four
out of five buildings in the strip have
been damaged or destroyed.
Pictures and videos have emerged of
tents sprouting up where homes have been
flattened, [موسيقى] families sweeping up
debris, children resting on dusty
mattresses among boards and concrete and
it's unknown how many bodies are buried
under the rebel.
‏To date, roughly 68,000 Palestinians
have been killed in the war. 18,000 of
them children. That's according to the
Hamasran Ministry of Health.
Around 9000 people have been reported
missing and they presumed dead under the
debris.
Several thousand are still not counted
among the dead.
Meanwhile, on Tuesday, the Israel
government accused Hamas of violating
the ceas. ‏The Israeli military launched
strikes that killed at least a hundred
people according to Gaza Health
officials. It was the deadliest day
since the ceasfire was agreed on 3 weeks
ago.
The ceas resumed Wednesday morning.
We be right back.
>> [موسيقى]
>> ‏Here's what else you need to know
today.
By Wednesday night, more than 20 people,
including children, were killed in Haiti
and five bodies were recovered in
Jamaica after Hurricane Melissa made
landfall this week.
>> [موسيقى]
>> ‏The hurricane was a category 5 storm
when it hit Jamaica on Tuesday before it
moved on to Cuba.
It has been downgraded to a category one
storm and beganning through the southern
part of the Bahamas on Wednesday
evening.
Officials said that more than 1 million
people in Jamaica or a third of the
population were directly affected by the
storm which devastated the island to
levels never seen before.
‏twoal prutors will put on leave after
they requed a stiff sent for a man who
showed up armed bar obama's house.
‏The man had previously been pardoned
for his role in storming the capital on
January 6th, and the prosecutors had
described him as being among the mob of
rioters in their sentencing memo.
The news was the latest act of
retribution by the Trump administration
against prosecutors in the US attorney's
office in Washington who worked on cases
relating to January 6th.
‏That campaign has also included
dismissals and emotions.
[موسيقى]
Today's episode was reported by Rochelle
Bonja. It was produced by Lindsay
Garrison, Rochelle Bonja, and Clare
Tennis Getter. It was edited by Maria
Burn with help from Michael Benis, Ben
Calhon and Page Cet. ‏It was fact
checked by Susan Lee. Contains music by
Marian Lozano, Dan Powell, Pat Mcusker,
Alishabe and Diane Wang and was
engineered by Moxley.
Research help by Sarah Mawad and Eric
Ter. Special thanks to Adam Razgon,
Yaraumi [موسيقى]
Adrian Carter, Tervin, Aon Boxerman Bu
Triple [موسيقى]
and Sad.
‏That's it for the daams.
See you tomorrow.
[موسيقى]